

#### RESEARCH SCHOLAR · DEEP/MACHINE LEARNING, COMPUTER NETWORKS, BRAIN COMPUTER INTERFACE

SIC 210, Gigabit Networking Laboratory, Kresit Building, CSE Department, IIT Bombay, India - 400076

□ (+91) 7053601960 | ■ abhiram@cse.iitb.ac.in | # abhiramsingh0.github.io/ | □ abhiramsingh0 | □ abhiram-singh

## Research Interest

#### MACHINE LEARNING, DEEP LEARNING, COMPUTER NETWORKS, BRAIN COMPUTER INTERFACE

My research focuses in the development of machine learning models to improve performance of computer networks. I am currently working on the intelligent computation models for routing in IP networks and developing scalable network verification tools. In past, I have also worked in the exciting area of the brain-computer interface.

# **Education**

CSE **Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.)**, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IIT Bombay) 2016 - Present

CSE **Master of Technology (M.Tech)**, National Institute of Technology Hamirpur (NIT Hamirpur)

CSE Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.), Oriental Institute of Science and Technology Bhopal (OIST Bhopal)

# **Projects**

### IIT Bombay Powai, Mumbai, India

### Ph.D Project 1 (Prof. Ashwin Gumaste)

Jan 2019 - PRESENT

2008 - 2012

- Formulated a graph neural network based deep learning model (Grafnet) to predict the output ports directly based on the IP address contained in the packets.
- Implemented Grafnet in Tensorflow and shown that Grafnet achieves high accuracy in predicting the correct output ports on a large network of 2000 nodes with 5 million IP addresses.
- Designed a single agent based deep reinforcement learning model (Trailnet) that learns to forward IP packets depending on the cost of packet forwarding from the neighbors.
- Implemented Trailnet in Tensorflow and shown that the cost estimates provided by Trailnet are close to optimal in a network of 145 nodes with 1 million IP addresses
- Created a machine learning model (Tapin) that takes destination IP address of a packet as its input and predicts the index of a rule in a forwarding table that provides the packet forwarding decision.
- We tested Tapin on a forwarding table containing 1 million entries. Tapin significantly reduced the search space to less than 500 entries for around 98% of table lookups.

### Ph.D Project 2 (Prof. Ashwin Gumaste)

Jan. 2020 - PRESENT

- Aim of project is to solve the network verification problem in a fast and scalable manner.
- Formulated a linear algebra based solution (LeSQnet) to find the set of reachable IP addresses between two nodes, detect loops and packet drops, model packet header transformations and check for ACL rules.
- Implemented LeSQnet in python and shown that after a rule update, LeSQnet checks for reachability within a millisecond on different networks containing millions of forwarding rules. LeSQnet is also shown to improve the complexity bounds for checking reachability.

### Ph.D Project 3 (Prof. Ashwin Gumaste)

Jan. 2017 - Jan. 2019

- Aim of project is to generate words that user speaks in mind without moving any body parts.
- Tested various features and machine learning models to classify a group of words based on their complexity. Used Python Scikit-learn framework to develop machine learning models and shown up to 11% performance improvement in correctly identifying imagined words over state-of-the-art methods on publicly available datasets.
- Designed graphics user interface using Python Tkinter library and integrated it with trained brain thought classifier to simulate real-time detection of brain thoughts.

### COURSE PROJECT (PROF. GANESH RAMAKRISHNAN)

Sept 2016 – Nov 2016

- Researched the problem of predicting answer of a question after learning from a set of sentences or from paragraphs.
- Implemented ANN, LSTM and Memory based neural network (Memn2n) in Tensorflow.
- Utilized Facebook bAbI dataset to show that Memn2n models outperforms other models in the task with 99% success rate on test data.

### Course Project (Prof. Virendra Singh)

Oct 2016 – Nov 2016

- Researched and implemented different branch predictors using Simple-scalar simulator written in C.
- Compared performance of implemented predictors with built in branch predictors on different benchmark programs provided with simulator.
- Shown that perceptron branch predictor outperformed other predictors with an average margin of 2-4% in miss prediction rate.

### Course Project (Prof. Bhaskaran Raman)

Mar 2016 – Apr 2016

- Researched different ways to predict the data transmission rate (TX rate) of a Wi-Fi device.
- Implemented Deep Learning model (in MatLab) to predict the behaviour of Operating System implemented algorithm for TX rate estimation.
- Shown that implemented model was able to achieve same performance in 60-65% cases to which data-rate prediction algorithm will converge.

- Researched problem to find average packet latency in a switch and measure switch throughput as a function of packet size.
- Simulated a switch of 16 ports (10Gbps) in Simpy and found that on increasing packet size, switch throughput increased and on the other hand average packet latency decreased.
- Did observed a considerable difference in average port to port latency of 0.6ms for packet size of 2000 Bytes and 250 Bytes.

#### NIT Hamirpur (Prof. T. P. Sharma)

Hamirpur, Himachal Pradesh, India

M.TECH PROJECT

Jul 2013 - Jul 2014

- Formulated an area coverage scheme in Wireless Sensor Network (WSN) to obtain full coverage of target area by providing 3 way connectivity of sensor nodes and simultaneously minimizing number of active sensor nodes.
- · Showed that the proposed approach can also provide network routing of data packets by providing tree structure among active sensor nodes.
- · Implemented all the functionalities in Omnet++ simulator and obtained state-of-the-art performance in the field.

# **Publications**

#### MACHINE LEARNING

- Abhiram Singh, Sidharth Sharma and Ashwin Gumaste, *Grafnet: Using Graph Neural Networks to Create Table-Less Routers*, Published in IEEE Transactions on Network Science and Engineering (TNSE)
- Abhiram Singh, Sidharth Sharma and Ashwin Gumaste, *Using Deep Reinforcement Learning for Routing in IP Networks*, Published in International Conference on Computer Communications and Networks (ICCCN 2021)
- Abhiram Singh, Aniruddha Kushwaha and Ashwin Gumaste, *TAP-IN: Table Address Prediction using Intelligent Learning for SDN Networks*, to be submitted in IEEE International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN 2022)
- Abhiram Singh and Ashwin Gumaste, Decoding Imagined Speech and Computer Control using Brain Waves, arXiv preprint arXiv:1911.04255, Published in Elsevier Journal of Neuroscience Methods (JNM 2021)
- Abhiram Singh and Ashwin Gumaste, Interpreting Imagined Speech Waves with Machine Learning techniques, arXiv preprint arXiv:2010.03360, to be submitted in Elsevier Journal of Neuroscience Methods

#### COMPUTER NETWORKS

- Abhiram Singh, Sidharth Sharma and Ashwin Gumaste, LeSQnet: Least Squares for Holistic and Expressive Verification of Networks, Under review in ACM SIGCOMM 2022.
- Abhiram Singh and T. P. Sharma, Position and Hop-count Assisted Full Coverage Control in Dense Sensor Networks, Published in Springer Journal
  of Wireless Networks 2015
- Abhiram Singh and T. P. Sharma, A survey on area coverage in wireless sensor networks, Published in International Conference on Control, Instrumentation, Communication and Computational Technologies (ICCICCT 2014)

#### PATENT APPLICATIONS

 Abhiram Singh, Sidharth Sharma and Ashwin Gumaste, Grafnet: Using Graph Neural Networks to Create Table-Less Routers, USPTO Publication Number: US-2021-0297324-A1.

# **Experience**

**Teaching Assistant** IIT Bombay, Mumbai, Jan 2016 – Present **Software Engineer** Aricent, Gurgaon, Oct 2014 – Aug 2015

**Teaching Assistant** NIT Hamirpur, Himachal Pradesh, July 2012 – Aug 2014

**Reviewer** IEEE Transactions on Cognitive Communications and Networking (TCCN), Wireless Networks (Springer Journal)

Talks Using Deep Reinforcement Learning for Routing in IP Networks (ICCCN 2021), A survey on area coverage in wireless sensor networks (ICCICCT 2014)

## Skills.

Programming Python, C/C++, MatLab, LaTeX

ML Framework Tensorflow, Scikit-learn

Simulators Simpy, Omnet++, Simple-scalar

# **National Examinations Cleared**

2012	All India Rank: 1115, The Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE)-Computer Science	India
2013	All India Rank: 528, The Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE)-Computer Science	India
Jun 2013	Assistant Professorship, National Eligibility Test (NET)-Computer Science and Applications	India
Dec 2013	Assistant Professorship, National Eligibility Test (NET)-Computer Science and Applications	India
Dec 2013	Junior Research Fellowship (JRF). National Eligibility Test (NET)-Computer Science and Applications	India